# 今天咱们做的什么菜你知道吗
Do you know what dish we're gonna cook today?
# 就觉得是茄子
I think it is eggplant
# 私房茄子
A private eggplant recipe
# 他既然要传承他肯定要切梳子花刀
As an inheritance, he's going to cut it in the "comb style"
# 对
Right
# 这就是咱北京茄子
That's our Beijing eggplant
# 没有籽儿
No seeds inside it
# 这个季节正好是吃茄子的时候
This is the reason to enjoy eggplants
# 茄子对身体确实好
Eggplant is indeed good for health
# 对啊 含铁巨大
Of course, it's rich in iron
# 你看
Watch it
# 这叫什么刀儿
How do you call this knife skill?
# 梳子花刀
The "comb style"
# 像梳子吗 拿来我看看
Does it look like a comb? Show me please
# 像梳子啊
Sure
# 拿一盆
Now, put it to a bowl
# 为什么这么切 它容易进味儿
Why do we cut it in this way? It allows flavor penetration
# 便于烹调 便于入味
Easier for cooking and flavor penetration
# 北京茄子不削皮
We don't peel Beijing eggplants
# 削了皮这茄子烧出来没有灵魂
If we peel this eggplant, we lose its soul
# 对 不好看
Right, not pretty anymore
# 烧完了 站不住
It's not solid after cooking
# 跟一滩烂泥似的
Just like a piece of rotten mud
# 其实好多营养都在茄子皮上呢
In fact, a lot of nutrition is in its skin
# 这个不弹粉就生炸
Just fry it, no need to add starch on it
# 然后我们就开始兑汁儿
Then, we start to prepare the sauce
# 先搁糖 够啦
Add sugar firstly. Enough now
# 叫 甜 咸 鲜 香
We call it sweet, salty, savory and aromatic
# 够不够 盐
Is salt enough?
# 两勺糖 一勺盐
Two spoons of sugar and a spoon of salt
# （花雕）酒
(Hua Diao) wine
# 你看看这是什么啊
Look, what's this?
# 醪糟
"Laozao" (rine wine)
# 醪糟要三到四勺
We need three or four spoons of "Laozao"
# 让所有茄子全展示出米的感觉
So that there will be rice grains all over the eggplant
# 酱油
Soy sauce
# 好
OK
# 老抽
Dark soy sauce
# 香油
Sesame oil
# 搁完香油怎么办啊
What's the next step then
# 葱 姜 蒜
Scallion, ginger, garlic
# 好
OK
# 这油现在已经到三成热了 四成了
The oil is about 100 °C now
# 还不下（茄子）啊
Not adding the eggplant yet?
# 不着急
No need to hurry
# 蒜片
Garlic
# 烧茄子少不了蒜
Garlic is essential for this dish
# 对
Sure
# 不要太多 多了之后显得菜乱
Not too much, otherwise the dish will be a little messy
# 一般这醪糟啊都是白汁的多
Generally speaking, the rice wine is always full of white sauce
# 葱花
Onion
# 这姜丝切这么溜土豆丝让我切
You're good at cutting ginger. Let me cut the potato later
# 这肉用腌制一下啊 不用
Should we marinate the meat? No
# 用不用调味啊 不用
Add condiment? No
# 这颜色就好啦
This color is perfect
# 淀粉
Starch
# 这三叔这茄子油可没少吃啊
San Shu, the eggplant has absorbed quite a lot of oil
# 是啊 油太大啦
Yeah, too oily now
# 这茄子炸到什么程度呢
How long do we need to fry the eggplants?
# 金黄色 金黄
Till golden brown
# 然后到这种程度呢
After reaching this level
# 还要复炸一下
We need to fry it again
# 捞出来 上上油温
Take it out and reheat the oil
# 这茄子吃的才香呢
Only after that, the eggplant will taste delicious
# 是香啊 绵
Of course it is
# 油可没少加
We also add lots of oil
# 你现在看它油大
Though it's oily now
# 待会把油温烧起来
After we reheat the oil
# 再一复炸的时候
And re-fry the eggplant
# 它这油就给逼出来了
The oil will be forced out from it
# 过去老师傅
In the past
# 我们这代人传承的老北京烧茄子
The traditional Beijing style braised eggplant passed to our generation
# 咱不能加淀粉
We shouldn't add starch (for the traditional recipe)
# 现在为什么加淀粉你知道么
Do you know why we add starch now?
# 为了方便卖这茄子
It's for selling the eggplant more easily
# 加上淀粉它不爱塌
It will be more solid after adding starch
# 撑盘儿
The appearance is more beautiful
# 咱这个烹制当时就吃
We eat it while we are cooking
# 为什么说好吃啊 对
- Because it is delicious
- Yeah
# 复炸一次
Re-fry now
# 毛豆
Edamame beans
# 搁豌豆行吗 行
How about pea？ Sure
# 就是配色
It's just for adding colors
# 中餐我还是那句话
There's something I always say about Chinese cuisine
# 没油真不好吃
You have to add enough oil to cook
# 提倡的是低油您提倡的是高油
Others are advocating low oil and you are advocating high oil
# 对 油要大啊
Definitely
# 留点底油
Keep a little bit oil in the wok
# 牛肉末
Ground beef
# 一定要煸透煸干
Gotta sweat it completely
# 煸香煸干于颗粒状
And make it aromatic and granular
# 大爷 请
Be my guest, Da Ye
# 一勺 两勺
One spoon Two spoons
# 勾汁 上芡
Toss it well with the slurry
# 快 出锅
Done
# 二哥来啦
Er Ge, Here we go
# 私房茄子 香气出来了啊
Private eggplant recipe. The aroma has spread all over now
# 再二次加热
Reheat it now
# 盖盖了你呐
Close the lid
# 好啦
OK
# 二伯要出手啦
Show time for Er Bai now
# 这是老饭骨私房茄子
This is Lao Fan Gu's private eggplant recipe
# 在三叔的基础上
Based on San Shu's work
# 我们仨刚才一致研究决定
We have just unanimously decided
# 这茄子在中国独一味儿
This is the most unique eggplant dish in China
# 你看看（加入醪糟）
Look at it (add rice wine)
# 拿筷子扒拉扒拉
Mix it with chopsticks?
# 这不用 就要这劲
No need to do it
# 看见没有
Just like this
# 取香
Extract the aroma
# 火燎（加入花雕）
Add Hua Diao
# 看看这香
Smells pretty good
# 满厨房都是香味啊大爷
The aroma is all over the kitchen, Da Ye
# 不是香味是酒味 酒香味
It's actually the aroma of wine
# 砂锅不能搁到木墩子上
Do not put a clay pot on a wooden surface
# 掀锅
Open the lid
# 关键就是这一拌一搅和
Mixing is a crucial step
# 香么
Smells good?
# 香香香
Absolutely
# 这茄子绝了
The eggplant is so delicious
# 又来一口
One more time
# 烫的直眨眼
Still so hot
# 就这种做法适合好多菜
This method is suitable for lots of other food
# 比如说丝瓜也可以这么做
Such as loofah
# 哎呦 丝瓜才好吃呢
You got it
# import ending.sbv 0:04:17.600